Guide to the Student Action With Farmworkers records, 1950-2020, bulk 1992-2016 RL.01128
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- SAF Student Projects, 1986-2018; 63 boxes
  - Into the Fields: Student Documentary Work, 1990-2015 and undated
    - Subject photos, undated, Folders 5-6 of 6 (Box 52)
    - Subject photos, undated (Box 113)
    - Subject photos (Box 113)
    - Photos by Wiggins and Thompson, 1990-1998 and undated (Box 113)
    - Janeth (2nd book) negatives (Box 52)
    - Staff photo slides, 4 folders (Box 52)
    - Unlabeled negatives, undated, 5 folders (Box 52)
      Negatives must be handled with gloves.
    - Film rolls (2), undated (Box 52)
      Please use gloves if viewing rolls.
    - Folklife Documentary Projects, 2000, 2013-2014
      Into the Fields Folklife projects, arranged in chronological groupings and within by the first student's last name, typically consist of interviews with farmworkers and their families, and documentation of living and working conditions in agricultural settings. Most projects were undertaken by two students or more.
      Audiovisual media (CDs and DVDs) accompany most projects, may contain still images, sound, artwork, document files, and moving images.
      Original audiovisual media closed to use. Digital use copies are available upon request. As these require advance preparation, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
      - The Heart of Tradition, by: Anna Harvin, 2000 (Box 53)
      - A Dedication to the Migrant Farmworkers, by: Bracero, 2000 (Box 136)
      - Overcoming the odds, by: Felipe Olivera Jr., 2000 (Box 94)
      - Overcoming the odds, Felipe Olivera, Jr., 2000 (Box 136)
      - Siga adelante, by: Steffany Barrior and Eliza Hardy, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Rompecabezas, by: Beatriz, Edith and Jaslina, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Aspire to Change, by: Eric Britton and Cindy Ramirez, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Brightening Horizons with Education, by: Lizeth Cruz and Carmen Ramirez, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Uniting Communities, by: Daniel Ferreyra and Yessenia Marqez, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Sembrar, Rezar, Cosechar, by: Kate Furgurson, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Untitled, by: Daniel Guzman-Ramos and Julie King, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Untitled, by: Mike Mian, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Untitled, by: Jocelyn Moratzka and Jasmine Romero, 2013 (Box 136)
      - A United Community, by: Jesus Nieto, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Untitled, by: Mimi Reiser, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Dos Trabajadores Con Un Gran Corazon, by: Clara Verela, 2013 (Box 136)
      - Juntos Podemos, by: Luis Acosta and Nick Snow, 2014 (Box 136)
        Includes 10 photographs
      - SAF Folklife Documentary Project, by: Yessy Burtos and Vianey Martinez, 2014 (Box 136)
        Includes 12 photographs
      - The Passion of Music Speaks What Cannot Be Expressed, by: Patti Cortez and Norma Garcia, 2014 (Box 136)
        Includes 8 photographs
      - The Farmworker Community, by: Michael Cunningham and Jose Guzman-Ramos, 2014 (Box 136)
        Includes 14 photographs
      - Cafe 71, by: Sarah Garrahan, 2014 (Box 136)
      - Community Through Networks, by: Vivi Gonzalez and Victor Gonzalez, 2014 (Box 136)
      - Anerin Mejia Roblero, by: Kimberly Luna and Cynthia Moreno, 2014 (Box 136)
      - Comunidad Entre Fronteras: Dona Teresa's Border Crossing Story, by: Mackenzie Man, 2014 (Box 136)
      - Two Sides of the Same Coin: The Story of Two Tobacco Farmers on Diverging Paths, by: Judith Mendez, 2014 (Box 136)
      - Return to the United, by: Andrea Mendoza, 2014 (Box 136)
      - Miguel: Folklife Interview, by: Gabe Pelly, 2014 (Box 136)
      - Untitled project (interview with Esmeralda), by: Miranda Schartz, 2014 (Box 136)
      - Rural Realities, by: Jesse Smith-Appelson, 2014 (Box 136)
        Includes 9 photographs
      - Hard work and Heartbreak, by: Devereaux Swaim, 2014 (Box 136)
    - ITF Documentary Projects, 2011-2015
      Into the Fields projects, arranged by last name of students or interns, typically consist of materials related to interviewing farmworkers and their families, and documenting living and working conditions. Folders can include transcripts of interviews, reflections on the interview process, photocopy reproductions or original photographic prints, and hard copies of blog posts written by the interns. Audiovisual media (CDs and DVDs) accompany many of the projects, and may contain still images, sound, and moving image formats.
      - Planting Seeds and Harvesting Hope, by Griselda Aguilar and Emily Dixon, 2012 (Box 137)
      - Voces del Silencio, by: Guillermo Alvarado and Lucero Galvan, 2012 (Box 137)
      - Hecho y Derecho, Como un Arbol, by: Shaoli Chaudhuri and Cesar Ramirez, 2012 (Box 137)
      - Para la Superacion no Existen Fronteras, Solo Dedicacion, by: Adriana Cuchillo and Bernardo Lopez, 2012 (Box 137)
      - Es Para Mi Familia, es Para Ellos, by: Hallie Dowling-Huppert, 2012 (Box 137)
      - With These Hands, Up Comes the Harvest, by: Dashiell Huebner, 2012 (Box 137)
      - Moviendo, Mudando, Trabajando, by: Justin Lyons and Pedro Zamora, 2012 (Box 137)
      - El Querer Pues es Poder Pero Sí, Sí Se Batalla, by: Freddy Olmos and Atlee Webber, 2012 (Box 137)
        Includes album with 25 photographs and 7 contact sheets
      - Sin Brazos Cruzados, by: Whitley Raney, 2012 (Box 137)
      - The Motive to Work, by: Emily Williams, 2012 (Box 137)
        Includes 35mm negatives
      - Los Campos en el Campo, by: Jessica Yon and Carolina Gonzalez, 2012 (Box 137)
        Includes 35mm negatives and photographs
    - Petrow-Freeman Documentary Award Winners (2013), 2010-2013
      Projects, arranged by last name of intern, typically consist of interviews by award-winning SAF interns with farmworkers and their families. Folders can include transcripts of interviews, reflections on the interview process, photocopy reproductions or original photographic prints, and hard copies of blog posts written by the interns. Audiovisual media (CDs and DVDs) form part of the materials, and may contain still images, sound, and moving image formats; they have been housed separately.
      - Untitled, by: Jennifer Cruz and Joanna Acevedo, 2010; 1 folder; 7 CDs (Box 137)
      - Harvesting Dreams, by: Adriana Sanchez, 2010; 1 folder; 1 CD (Box 137)
      - Retorno 360, by: Tony Macias, 2012; 1 folder; 2 CDs; 3 DVDs (Box 137)
      - Meet Your Farmworker, by: Atlee Webber and others, 2013; 1 folder; 2 DVDs (Box 137)
    - ITF Folklife Documentary Projects, 2015
      Projects, arranged by last name of intern, typically consist of interviews by SAF summer interns with farmworkers and their families, usually in migrant camps. Folders can include transcripts of interviews, reflections on the interview process, photocopy reproductions or original photographic prints, and hard copies of blog posts written by the interns. Audiovisual media (CDs and DVDs) accompany many of the projects, and may contain still images, sound, and moving image formats; these have been removed and housed separately.
      - Hector Sanchez: Un pollito tabaquero, by: Marlene Aboytes, Caroline LaFave, 2015; 1 folder; 1 DVD (Box 142)
      - Lilcat documentary project [interviews with two migrant brothers, Miguel and Demetrio], by: Liliana Altamirano and Catherine Crowe, 2015 (Box 142)
      - SAF Documentary [interviews with a farmworker], by: Katia Chavira and Araceli Suarez, 2015; 1 folder; 1 DVD (Box 142)
      - "I am a farmer," by: Jorge Hernandez, Lupe Saldana, 2015 (Box 142)
      - La vida de Edgar A. Montes, un nuevo vida cómo un contratado, by: José A. Hernandez and Brenda Ramirez, 2015 (Box 142)
      - SAF Documentary [interviews with farmworkers], by: Ana Jarmillo, 2015 (Box 142)
      - SAF Documentary [interviews with farmworker in S.C.], by: John Madden, 2015 (Box 142)
      - Untitled [interviews with farmworker couple], by: Silvana Marr-Madariaga, 2015 (Box 142)
      - "Soy una luchadora," by: Karla Mendoza, 2015 (Box 142)
      - SAF Documentary [interviews with two farmworkers], by: Elena Perez, Emma Cathell, 2015 (Box 142)
      - SAF Documentary [interview with female former farmworker], by: Fidel Ruiz, Emily Blackshire, 2015 (Box 142)
      - Mario: Su vida, su trabajo, y su querido Mexico, by: Miranda Russell, Eric Alvarez, 2015 (Box 142)
      - Louis Souverain: Always moving forward [oral history], by: Rachel Taylor, 2015 (Box 142)
  - Into the Fields: Journals and Guided Reflections, 1995-2014
    Arranged in date order. Contains journals, notebooks, and worksheets kept by interns for the purpose of taking notes during the program, drafting blog entries, and for reflecting on the internship and documentary process.
    - PACE (Preventing Agricultural Chemical Exposure in NC Farmworkers) (Box 94)
    - PACE photo journal, circa 1997 (Box 137)
      Hand-made student journal booklet with black construction paper covers and pages, containing black-and-white glossy photo prints and typed captions that illustrate the process of training student interviewers and conducting interviews among farmworkers.
    - Journals and Guided Reflections, 1995-2001 (Box 54)
    - Journals and Guided Reflections, 2005-2009 (Box 55)
    - Journals and Guided Reflections, 2009, and undated (Box 56)
    - Journals and Guided Reflections, 2010-2013; 4 folders (Box 112)
    - Faces of Mount Olive, by Stephen Chin, 2000 (Box 94)
    - Faces of Mount Olive, photo essay album, by Stephen Chin, 2000 (Oversize-box 147)
      Black cloth-covered accordion-bound album, approximately 9 1/2 x 13 inches, with glossy black-and-white photographs and detailed captions illustrating working conditions at the Mount Olive Pickle Company in North Carolina. Photographs measure roughly 5x7 inches, and are mounted one to a page.
    - FLOC por la Justicia (Box 94)
    - Notebook, Selena Ibarra, ITF summer intern, Summer 2014 (Box 137)
  - AIM - Farmworker Class, 1993-2003 and undated; 3 boxes
    Digital material moved to the Audio/Visual and Digital Material Subseries.
    - Administrative/general information, undated (Box 57)
    - Readings, 1993-2002 (Box 57)
    - Readings, undated (Box 57)
    - Projects, 2001-2002 (Box 57)
    - Project 2002: Mi Hogar (Box 58)
    - Projects, 2002 and undated (Box 59)
    - 2001 individual student files (Box 59)
    - Conferences and retreats 1998-2003 and undated (Box 59)
  - Levante Project materials, 1994-2018 and undated
    SAF's Levante Leadership Institute uses theatre and arts to provide migrant and farmworker youth in rural North Carolina with opportunities to build self-esteem, develop leadership skills, discuss agriculture and farmworker history, and prepare them for higher education.
    Series contains Levante administrative files as well as audiovisual documentation of theatre projects. Files can include meeting notes, planning, program administration records, student reflection journals and self-portraits, student applications, and program evaluations.
    A/V material has been moved to the Audio/Visual and Digital Material Subseries.
    Access to materials in student projects series is restricted and can only be authorized by SAF.
    Original media have been separated and are closed to use; digital files are available on request. As they require advance preparation, please contact the Rubenstein Library vbefore coming to use this collection.
    - 1994-2001, approximately 50 folders (Box 60)
    - 2002-2011 and undated, approximately 50 folders (Box 61)
    - 2009-2012, 3 folders (Box 112)
      Evaluations
    - Levante, 2010-2011 (Box 97)
    - Levante Leadership Institute and SOS orientation, 2010-2011 (Box 97)
    - 2012-2014 and undated, 4 folders (Box 113)
      Journals and reflections, parent meeting
    - Cloth banners, 4 banners (Box 63)
    - 2011-2013, 16 folders (Box 138)
      Chiefly leadership institutes applications and participant folders, but also includes a folder with TLSS pre- and post-tests and surveys, as well as planning materials for an SAF Migrant Student coordinator.
    - 2014-2015, 11 folders (Box 138)
      Levante and other leadership programs (SSI, Juntos, Solidaridad, LLI) files include LLI student applications, meeting agendas, a few participant files, social media policy, and other administrative records. Also includes folder with True Colors Workshop materials on discovering leadership style, a folder for a community meeting on child labor project, and a folder for a NC Central Latino Advisory Group meeting.
    - 2014-2015 (cont.), 5 folders (Box 139)
      Materials for Levante (LLI) and Juntos programs include a Levante manual, applications, group evaluations, surveys, workshops. Also includes a conference folder on family engagement and early childhood and an "ABC project" collection of alphabet cards with one word each, illustrated by a mounted color snapshots of SAF students, objects, and activities.
    - 2015-2017, 4 folders (Box 139)
      Planning, applications, pre- and post-tests, and one folder with 2016-2017 end-of-program survey.
    - Reflection journals, 2014-2016; 11 folders (Box 140)
      Notebook journals by high-school age SAF students typically contain class notes on the basics of migrant labor issues, the workings of state politics, and personal habits and health; questions about self-identity and personal goals; interviews with fellow students; and blog post drafts.
    - Reflection journals and other class materials, 2016-2018; 6 folders (Box 141)
      In addition to two notebook/journals, contains student work such as self-portraits, poetry, a timeline, and a handprint exercise.
    - Levante self-portrait, 2016 (Oversize-box 147)
      Two color snapshots mounted on construction paper: one of a bridge, and one of five students, along with words framing the pictures.
    - Levante self-portrait collages, 2016-2017 (Oversize-box 148)
      Self-identity narratives composed of snapshots and labels mounted on construction papers, captioned by SAF students.
    - Levante, Literacy Through Photography photographic narrative, 2016 (Oversize-box 148)
      Nine paper sheets measuring 11x17 inches, bearing color photographic montages describing an SAF student's family and origins. English and Spanish captions and labels.
- Audiovisual Materials, circa 1986-2015
  Chiefly contains audio, visual, and digital material from Into the Fields, AIM, and Levante documentary projects created by interns and students. Typical content includes: theater recordings; recorded interviews; digital photographs; digital videos; artwork; and music and poetry.
  A few items are more generally related to Student Action with Farmworkers events or resources rather than to student projects, such as a copy of the 1986 documentary film "Wrath of Grapes" about the Chavez and United Farmworkers campaign against dangerous working conditions for farmworkers.
  Media formats in the collection include: VHS cassettes, cassette tapes, computer diskettes, mini digital video disks, mini-disks, one film reel, and many CDs and DVDs. Some but not all media have been migrated to a server; digital files are available on request.
  Students also made use of an SAF server to upload electronic project files. These have not yet been transferred to the library collection.
  Project materials are closed to use unless permission expressly granted by donor.
  Original media are closed to use. Digital use copies are available on request; advance notice required. In addition, transcripts or summaries of oral histories and other interviews are often available in student project folders.
  Please contact the Rubenstein Library for assistance before coming to use this collection.
  - Wrath of Grapes film reel, 1986? (Box 24, Film RL.01128-F16-0001)
    Open for research. However, original film is closed to use. A viewing copy must be made for access. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this material.
  - Theater release forms, transcripts, tape logs, 2004-2005, 7 folders (Box 62)
  - Rough cut and back-up file CDs and DVDs (Box 62)
  - Levante: Theater for Social Change (rough cut) 15:55, VHS, 2005 April 4 (Box 62)
  - Levante: Theater for Social Change / Levante: Teatro Para Cambio Social (Bilingual, English-Spanish) 46:25, VHS, 2005 April 4 (Box 62)
  - Levante Theater for Social Change / Teatro Para Cambio Social (Bilingual, English, Spanish), TRT 46:25, mini-DV, 2005 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0001, Video-file Levante Theater for Social Change.mov)
  - SAF01: Rehearsal - warm ups, run-through, self intros for performance, mini-DV, June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0002, Video-file SAF 01.mov)
  - SAF02: Group Interview #1 (in auditorium), outside warm-ups, run-through in auditorium, mini-DV June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0003, Video-file SAF 02.mov)
  - SAF03: Run-through (outside), Group Interview #2 (in library), mini-DV June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0004, Video-file SAF 03.mov)
  - SAF04: Group Interview #2 continued, photos from booklet upon which characters are based, room tone, mini-DV June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0005, Video-file SAF 04.mov)
  - SAF05: Interview with Omar Lainez, en route to performance site, setting up, warming up, mini-DV June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0006, Video-file SAF 05.mov)
  - SAF06: Performance - entire play on tripod from one location; interviews with 4 farmworkers, mini-DV June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0007, Video-file SAF 06.mov)
  - SAF07: En route to performance site, setting up, warming up, mini-DV June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0008, Video-file SAF 07.mov)
  - SAF08: Performance - hand held, from many different places, shots of audience; interviews with 3 farmworkers: #1 is in-camera mic; #2 and #4 are have lav mic; #3 was not taped by this camera, mini-DV June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0009, Video-file SAF 08.mov)
  - SAF09: Guitar music (and Legal Aid front door), mini-DV June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0010, Video-file SAF 09.mov)
  - SAF10: Interview with Laxmi Haynes, SAF signs, red smilies, mini-DV, June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0011, Video-file SAF 10.mov)
  - Gigantes en los Campos: Interview with Omar Laines, performance #1 at un campo, DAT, June 2004 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0022, Audio-file RL01128_GigantesEnLosCampos_OmarLaines_01.aif; RL01128_GigantesEnLosCampos_OmarLaines_02.aif)
    CD use copy available.
  - Gigantes Original 2003, Hi8, 2003 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0012, Video-file Gigantes original 2003.mov)
  - Untitled, Hi8, undated (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0013, Video-file untitled 8mm.mov)
  - ¿Que Saco de la Escuela?, Hi8, undated (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0014, Video-file Que Saco de la Escuela.mov)
  - ¿Que Saco de la Escuela?, Gardner - Webb University, VHS-C, June 2000 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0015, Video-file 2000-06-21 Que Saco de la Escuela.mov)
  - ¿Que Saco de la Escuela?, Nash County Festival Latino, VHS-C, July 2000 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0016, Video-file 2000-07-30 Que Saco de la Escuela Festival Latino.mov)
  - Farm Worker Awareness Week, Duke, VHS-C, March 2001 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0017, Video-file 2001-03-28 Farmworkers Awareness Week Rally.mov)
  - Los Vendidos performed at 2001 AIM Conference, VHS-C, March 2001 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0018, Video-file Los Vencticles 2001 AIM Conference.mov)
  - Los Vendidos, second Nash County performance, VHS-C, 2001 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0019, Video-file Los Vencticles Nash County Second Performance.mov)
  - Los Vendidos performed at labor camps in Nash County, VHS-C, 2001 (Box 62, Digital-materials RL01128-SET-0020, Video-file Los Vencticles performed at Labor Camps in Nash Co.mov)
  - ITF audio tapes, 1990-2004, 3 containers (Box 65)
  - ITF audio tapes, 2004-2005 and undated, 3 containers (Box 66)
  - ITF documentary discs, 2000-2004 and undated (Box 67)
  - ITF administrative and miscellaneous project discs, 1997-2003 and undated (Box 67)
  - ITF Nuestras Historias mini discs, 2006-2008 (Box 67)
  - ITF documentary CDs, 2000-2004 and undated (Box 68)
  - 2002 ITF guided reports (Box 69)
  - ITF documentary projects, 2005, 3 folders (Box 69)
  - ITF 2006 documentary intern Bart Evans (Box 69)
  - ITF SAF/CDS Our Stories/Our Dreams Documentary Project, 1 folders (Box 69)
  - ITF Documentary Project, 2006-2007; 7 folders (Box 69)
  - ITF Folklife Documentary Project, 1 of 2 (Box 69)
  - ITF Folklife Documentary Project, 2 of 2 (Box 70)
  - ITF Miscellaneous Media (Box 70)
  - ITF W-3 Work with Three Students (Box 70)
  - ITF 2008 Folklife Documentary Project (Box 70)
  - ITF 2008 Documentary Project, 7 folders (Box 70)
  - AIM 2001 NC Farmworker Class, Justin Fishkin (Box 70)
  - AIM 2001 NC Farmworker Class, Beth O'Donnell (Box 70)
  - AIM 2001 NC Farmworker Class, Alison Blaine (Box 70)
  - Levante rough cut and back-up file, CDs and DVDs (Box 70)
  - 1. Plantation Legislature; 2. Migrant Lay Health Advisors: A Strategy, 16:15, VHS, 1987 (Box 104)
  - Catholic Communications Network, Season of the Migrants, 19:20, VHS, undated (Box 104)
  - Milagritos... Little Miracles: When Communities Create Farmworker Housing, 16:00, VHS, 1998 (Box 104)
  - Justice on the Table: Resources and Discussion Guides for Schools and Religious Audiences, 25:00, VHS, 2003 (Box 104)
  - Media from Into The Fields and other projects, 1993-2011; 35 diskettes, 25 minidisks, 17 CD-Rs (Box 105)
    Access to materials in this series is restricted and can only be authorized by Student Action with Farmworkers administration.
    Original audiovisual media are closed to use. These materials have not been migrated to a library server. Digital files are available on request. As they must be prepared well in advance, please contact the Rubenstein Library prior to coming to use this collection.
  - Media from Into The Fields student projects, 2009-2013; 66 audiovisual items 1 box 38 optical disks; 1 audio cassette; 14 mini digital video cassettes; 13 mini-disks (Box 116)
    RL.01128-OP-0001 to OP-0038; RL.01128-MDV-0001 to MDV-0014; RL.01128-MD-0001 to MD-0013.
    Access to materials is restricted and can only be authorized by Student Action with Farmworkers administration.
    Original audiovisual media are closed to use. Contents have been migrated to a library server in 2016. Digital files are available on request. As they must be prepared in advance, please contact the Rubenstein Library prior to coming to use this collection.
  - Media from Into The Fields student projects, 2012-2013; 78 disks 1 box CDs and DVDs (optical disks) (Box 143)
    RL.01128-OP-0039 to RL.01128-OP-0116
    Original audiovisual media are closed to use. Digital files are available on request. As they must be prepared in advance, please contact the Rubenstein Library prior to coming to use this collection.
  - Media from Into The Fields and Folklife student projects, 2012-2015; 11 disks 1 box CDs and DVDs (optical disks) (Box 144)
    RL.01128-OP-0117 to RL.01128-OP-0127
- Printed Material, 1978-2016 and undated; 14 boxes
  Contains Student Action with Farmworkers (SAF) publications, press coverage, and publicity, as well as a rich collection of publications originating from local, regional, and national organizations. Many of these were housed in binders and resource files in SAF's offices.
  Formats include articles, reports, data sheets, directories, clippings, newsletters, and ephemeral publications (fliers, brochures) related to farmworker and migrant labor issues. There are also a handful of student theses, and a selection of children's books. Many of the items are English and Spanish bilingual publications.